So, what I'd like to talk about is something
ما أود الحديث عنه هو شيء
that was very dear to Kahn's heart, which is:
كان هذا عزيز جدا على قلب كارين، الذي هو
how do we discover what is really particular about a project?
كيف نكتشف ما هو خاص حقا عن اي مشروع؟
How do you discover the uniqueness of a project as unique as a person?
كيف تكتشف تميز المشروع، فريد من نوعه مثل أي شخص،
Because it seems to me that finding this uniqueness
لأنه يبدو لي أن البحث عن هذا التميز
has to do with dealing with the whole force of globalization;
له علاقة في التعامل مع القوة الكاملة من العولمة:
that the particular is central to finding the uniqueness of place
هذا على وجه الخصوص أمر أساسي لإيجاد مكان للتميز
and the uniqueness of a program in a building.
وتميز برنامج في المبنى.
And so I'll take you to Wichita, Kansas,
ولذا فإنني سوف أخذكم إلى ويتشيتا بولاية كنساس،
where I was asked some years ago to do a science museum
حيث طلب مني قبل عدة سنوات على القيام بمتحف للعلوم
on a site, right downtown by the river.
في موقع على النهر.
And I thought the secret of the site was to make the building of the river, part of the river.
و اعتقدت أن سر الموقع هو جعل البناء جزء من النهر.
Unfortunately, though, the site was separated from the river by McLean Boulevard
على الرغم من سوء الحظ، كانت جادة ماكلين تفصل الموقع عن النهر.
so I suggested, "Let's reroute McLean,"
واذلك اقترحت أنا أن نقوم بتغيير مسار ماكلين.
and that gave birth instantly to Friends of McLean Boulevard.
والتي ولدت على الفور اصدقاء جادة ماكلين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it took six months to reroute it.
وقد اتغرق ستة اشهر لتغير مساره.
The first image I showed the building committee was
كانت اول صوره اريتها للجنة البناء هي
this astronomic observatory of Jantar Mantar in Jaipur
المرصد الفلكي من جانتار المنطار في جايبور،
because I talked about what makes a building a building of science.
لأنني تحدثت عن، ما يجعل بناء مبنى من العلم؟
And it seemed to me that this structure -- complex, rich and yet
ويبدو لي أن هذا الهيكل،ممتلئ ومعقد وحتى الآن
totally rational: it's an instrument -- had something to do with science,
عقلاني تماما، انها أداة -- كان ليفعل شيئا مع العلم،
and somehow a building for science should be different and unique and speak of that.
وعلى نحو ما ينبغي أن يكون البناء للعلوم مختلف وفريد من نوعه.
And so my first sketch after I left was to say,
و بعد رسمي الاول، غادرت لاقول،
"Let's cut the channel and make an island and make an island building."
لنقم بقطع القناة وبناء الجزيرة ، وجعل المبنى جزيرة.
And I got all excited and came back, and
ولقد تحمست ورجعت و
they sort of looked at me in dismay and said, "An island?
نظروا الى في حالة فزع وقالو: جزيرة؟
This used to be an island -- Ackerman Island --
لقد كانت هذه جزيرة، جزيرة اكيرمان،
and we filled in the channel during the Depression to create jobs."
وملأنا نحن القناة خلال فترة الكساد لخلق فرص عمل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so the process began and they said,
وبذلك يقال ان العملية قد بدئت
"You can't put it all on an island;
لا تستطيع وضعها كلها بالجزيرة،
some of it has to be on the mainland because
بعضها يجب ان يكون في الجزيرة الرئيسية لانه
we don't want to turn our back to the community."
لا نريد ان ندير ظهرنا لمجتمعنا.
And there emerged a design: the galleries sort of forming an island
وبهذا تم دمج التصميم، المعرض الذي يشبه الجزيرة،
and you could walk through them or on the roof.
وتستطيع المشي بينهم او على السطح،
And there were all kinds of exciting features:
وكان هناك كل الميزات المثيرة.
you could come in through the landside buildings,
تستطيع ان تدخل من خلال المباني الجانبية،
walk through the galleries into playgrounds in the landscape.
امشي بجوار المعارض باتجاه ساحة اللعب، هناك الطبيعة.
If you were cheap you could walk on top of a bridge to the roof,
اذا كنت بخيلا تستطيع المشي فوق الجسر الى السطح،
peek in the exhibits and then get totally seduced,
واخذ نظره على المعارض و ستغرى،
come back and pay the five dollars admission.
بالعودة ودفع 5 دولارات رسم الدخول.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the client was happy -- well, sort of happy
وكان العميل سعيدا، او هكذا،
because we were four million dollars over the budget, but essentially happy.
لاننا تخطينا الميزانية باربعة ملايين دولار، ولكن في النهاية سعيد.
But I was still troubled, and I was troubled because I felt this was capricious.
ولكننى مازلت في المشاكل، وايضا كنت متقلب المزاج.
It was complex, but there was something capricious about its complexity.
لقد كانت معقدة، ولكن هناك شئ متقلب في هذا التعقيد.
It was, what I would say, compositional complexity,
وكان، ما أود أن أقول، التعقيد التركيبي
and I felt that if I had to fulfill what I talked about --
وشعرت أنه إذا كان لي لتحقيق ما تحدثت عنه،
a building for science -- there had to be some kind of a generating idea,
مبنى للعلوم، كان ليكون هناك نوع من فكرة توليد --
some kind of a generating geometry.
نوع من هندسة التوليد.
And this gave birth to the idea of having toroidal generating geometry,
و ولد هذا فكرة وجود ملف حلقي لهندسة التوليد،
one with its center deep in the earth for the landside building
مع وسطها -- واحدة مع مركزها في أعماق الأرض للبناء الجانبي،
and a toroid with its center in the sky for the island building.
وحلقي مع مركزه في السماء لبناء الجزيرة.
A toroid, for those who don't know,
وحلقي، بالنسبة لأولئك الذين لا يعرفون،
is the surface of a doughnut or, for some of us, a bagel.
هو سطح كعكات، أو بالنسبة للبعض منا الخبز الحلقي.
And out of this idea started spinning off many,
وبدأت هذه الفكرة بتحريك كثير،
many kinds of variations of different plans and possibilities,
وكثير من الخطط المختلفة والاحتمالات،
and then the plan itself evolved in relationship to the exhibits,
ثم تطورت الخطة نفسها في العلاقة مع المعروضات،
and you see the intersection of the plan with the toroidal geometry.
وترى تقاطعه مع خطة الهندسة الحلقية.
And finally the building -- this is the model.
وأخيرا البناء -- وهذا هو النموذج.
And when there were complaints about budget, I said,
وقلت عندما كانت هناك شكاوى حول الميزانية،
"Well, it's worth doing the island because you get twice for your money: reflections."
حسنا ، انها تستحق بذل الجهد في الجزيرة لأنك تحصل على ضعفي أموالك -- الانعكاسات.
And here's the building as it opened,
وهنا افتتاح البناء،
with a channel overlooking downtown, and as seen from downtown.
مع قناة تطل على وسط المدينة، وكما يتضح من وسط المدينة،
And the bike route's going right through the building,
و طريق للدراجات يمر من خلال المبنى،
so those traveling the river would see the exhibits and be drawn to the building.
حتى أولئك الذين يسافرون بالنهر سيشاهدون المعروضات وينجذبون إلى المبنى.
The toroidal geometry made for a very efficient building:
هندسة البناء الحلقية كونت مباني فعالة جدا.
every beam in this building is the same radius, all laminated wood.
كل شعاع في هذا المبنى هو نصف القطر نفسه، الخشب الرقائقي جميع.
Every wall, every concrete wall is resisting the stresses and supporting the building.
كل جدار، كل جدار إسمنتي، يقاوم الضغوط ويدعم البناء.
Every piece of the building works.
كل قطعة من اعمال بناء.
These are the galleries with the light coming in through the skylights,
هذه هي صالات العرض مع ضوء قادم من خلال مناور
and at night, and on opening day.
وفي الليل، ويوم الافتتاح.
Going back to 1976.
نعود إلى 1976 --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In 1976, I was asked to design a children's memorial museum
-- في عام 1976 طلب مني أن تصميم المتحف التذكاري للأطفال
in a Holocaust museum in Yad Vashem in Jerusalem,
في متحف المحرقة في ياد فاشيم في القدس،
which you see here the campus.
الذي تراه هنا -- في الحرم الجامعي.
I was asked to do a building,
وطلب مني القيام بناء،
and I was given all the artifacts of clothing and drawings.
وأعطيت كل التحف والملابس والرسومات.
And I felt very troubled.
وشعرت باضطراب شديد.
I worked on it for months and I couldn't deal with it
لقد عملت على ذلك لعدة أشهر ولم اتمكن من التعامل معها،
because I felt people were coming out of the historic museum,
لأنني شعرت وكان الناس يخرجون من المتحف التاريخي،
they are totally saturated with information
مشبعين تماما بالمعلومات،
and to see yet another museum with information,
ورؤية أخرى مع متحف المعلومات ،
it would make them just unable to digest.
وسوف تجعلهم غير قادرين على الهضم.
And so I made a counter-proposal:
وقدمت لذلك اقتراحا مضادا.
I said, "No building." There was a cave on the site; we tunnel into the hill,
قلت، لا بناء، وكان هناك كهف على موقع النفق ونحن، في التل،
descend through the rock into an underground chamber.
تنحدر من خلال الصخور في غرفة تحت الأرض.
There's an anteroom with photographs of children who perished
هناك في الردهة مع صور الأطفال الذين لقوا حتفهم،
and then you come into a large space.
ثم تجد مساحة كبيرة.
There is a single candle flickering in the center;
هناك شمعة واحدة، تخفق في المركز.
by an arrangement of reflective glasses, it reflects into infinity in all directions.
من هذا الترتيب من الزجاج العاكس، وهو يعكس في اللانهاية في كل الاتجاهات.
You walk through the space, a voice reads the names,
أنت تمشي من خلال الفضاء، وصوت يقرأ الأسماء،
ages and place of birth of the children.
الأعمار ومكان ولادة الأطفال.
This voice does not repeat for six months.
هذا الصوت لا يتكرر لمدة ستة أشهر.
And then you descend to light and to the north and to life.
وتنحدر ثم للضوء وإلى الشمال ، وإلى الحياة.
Well, they said, "People won't understand,
حسنا ، قالوا، الناس سوف لا تفهم --
they'll think it's a discotheque. You can't do that."
سوف يعتقدون انها مرقص، لا يمكنك أن تفعل ذلك.
And they shelved the project. And it sat there for 10 years,
و وضعوا المشروع على الرف. و جلس هناك لمدة 10 سنوات.
and then one day Abe Spiegel from Los Angeles,
ثم في احد الايام، إد شبيجل، من لوس انجليس،
who had lost his three-year-old son at Auschwitz,
الذي كان قد فقد ابنه لمدة ثلاث سنوات من عمره في أوشفيتز ،
came, saw the model, wrote the check and it got built 10 years later.
رأى النموذج، كتب الصك، وحصلت على 10 سنوات بناء في وقت لاحق.
So, many years after that in 1998,
سنوات عديدة بعد ذلك، في عام 1998 ،
I was on one of my monthly trips to Jerusalem
كنت في واحدة من رحلاتي الشهرية الى القدس،
and I got a call from the foreign ministry saying,
وتلقيت مكالمة من وزارة الخارجية قائلا :
"We've got the Chief Minister of the Punjab here.
لدينا رئيس وزراء ولاية البنجاب هنا.
He is on a state visit. We took him on a visit to Yad Vashem,
وهو في زيارة دولة. اخذناه في زيارة لياد فاشيم.
we took him to the children's memorial; he was extremely moved.
ثم اقتادناه الى النصب التذكاري للأطفال، وتأثر للغاية.
He's demanding to meet the architect. Could you come down and meet him in Tel Aviv?"
و هو يطلب من المهندس المعماري تلبية طلبه للاجتماع به في تل أبيب؟
And I went down and Chief Minister Badal said to me,
وذهبت ، ورئيس وزراء بادال قال لي،
"We Sikhs have suffered a great deal, as you have Jews.
لقد عانينا نحن السيخ كثيرا، كما اليهود.
I was very moved by what I saw today.
وتأثرت جدا بما رأيته اليوم.
We are going to build our national museum to tell the story of our people;
سوف نقوم ببناء المتحف الوطني ليحكي قصة شعبنا؛
we're about to embark on that.
نحن على وشك الشروع في ذلك.
I'd like you to come and design it."
أريد منك أن تأتي وتقوم بتصميمه.
And so, you know, it's one of those things that you don't take too seriously.
وهكذا، كما تعلمون ، انها واحدة من تلك الأشياء التي لا تأخذها على محمل الجد.
But two weeks later, I was in this little town, Anandpur Sahib,
ولكن بعد أسبوعين كنت في هذه المدينة الصغيرة، صاحب انادابر
outside Chandigarh, the capital of the Punjab,
خارج شانديغار، عاصمة ولاية البنجاب،
and the temple and also next to it the fortress
والمعبد، وأيضا مقابل القلعة
that the last guru of the Sikhs, Guru Gobind, died in
حيث توفي المعلم الأخير للسيخ، جورو نانكاني،
as he wrote the Khalsa, which is their holy scripture.
كما انه كتب الخالصة، وهو كتابهم المقدس.
And I got to work and they took me somewhere down there,
وحصلت على العمل وأخذوني في مكان ما هناك،
nine kilometers away from the town and the temple,
تسعة كيلومترات من المدينة والمعبد،
and said, "That's where we have chosen the location."
وقال لقد اخترنا هذا الموقع.
And I said, "This just doesn't make any sense.
وقلت، هذا لا يقدم أي معنى.
The pilgrims come here by the hundreds of thousands --
الحجاج يأتون إلى هنا من قبل مئات وآلاف --
they're not going to get in trucks and buses and go down there.
انهم لن يركبوا في الشاحنات والحافلات للذهاب الى هناك.
Let's get back to the town and walk to the site."
دعونا نعود إلى المدينة وسيرا على الاقدام الى الموقع.
And I recommended they do it right there, on that hill
وأوصيت ان يبنوا هناك ، على تلك التلة،
and this hill, and bridge all the way into the town.
وهذا التل، وجسر على طول الطريق الى البلدة.
And, as things are a little easier in India, the site was purchased within a week
وكانت الأمور أسهل قليلا في الهند، اشتري الموقع في غضون أسبوع،
and we were working.
وكنا نعمل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And my proposal was to split the museum into two --
وكان اقتراحي لتقسيم المتحف الى قسمين :
the permanent exhibits at one end, the auditorium, library,
المعروضات الدائمة في نهاية واحدة، وقاعة ومكتبة،
and changing exhibitions on the other --
وتغيير المعارض من ناحية أخرى.
to flood the valley into a series of water gardens
لتفييض الوادي إلى سلسلة من الحدائق المائية،
and to link it all to the fort and to the downtown.
وربط كل ذلك إلى حصن وإلى وسط المدينة.
And the structures rise from the sand cliffs --
والهياكل ترتفع من المنحدرات الرملية.
they're built in concrete and sandstones; the roofs are stainless steel --
بنيت في الخرسانة والحجر الرملي، وأسقف مصنوعة من الفولاذ المقاوم للصدأ.
they are facing south and reflecting light towards the temple itself,
انهم يواجهون الجنوب والتي تعكس الضوء في اتجاه المعبد نفسه،
pedestrians crisscross from one side to the other.
مسار المشاة متقاطع من جانب واحد على الآخر.
And as you come from the north, it is all masonry growing out of the sand cliffs
و عندما تقبل من الشمال ترى جميع البناء المتنامي من المنحدرات الرملية،
as you come from the Himalayas and evoking the tradition of the fortress.
كأنك تأتي من جبال الهيمالايا، وتستحضر القلاع التقليدية.
And then I went away for four months
وثم ذهبت بعيدا لمدة أربعة أشهر،
and there was going to be groundbreaking.
وهناك كان فتحا على وشك أن يحدث.
And I came back and, lo and behold, the little model I'd left behind
وعدت، ولو لمح، ونموذج صغير كنت قد تركت وراءي
had been built ten times bigger for public display on site
قد تم بناءه أكبر بعشر مرات للعرض العام على موقع،
and ... the bridge was built!
وشيد الجسر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Within the working drawings!
في إطار عمل رسومات!
And half a million people gathered for the celebrations;
ونصف مليون شخص تجمعوا لحضور الاحتفالات،
you can see them on the site itself as the foundations are beginning.
يمكنك رؤيتها على الموقع نفسه حيث بدأت المؤسسات.
I was renamed Safdie Singh. And there it is under construction;
كنت تسمية سفيديا سينغ، وهناك هو قيد الإنشاء --
there are 1,800 workers at work and it will be finished in two years.
كنت هناك 1800 عامل في العمل، وسيتم الانتهاء منها في غضون عامين.
Back to Yad Vashem three years ago. After all this episode began,
عودة الى ياد فاشيم منذ ثلاث سنوات. بدأ كل شيء بعد هذه الحلقة ،
Yad Vashem decided to rebuild completely the historic museum
قررت ياد فاشيم لإعادة بناء المتحف التاريخي تماما،
because now Washington was built -- the Holocaust Museum in Washington --
لانه واشنطن تبني الآن، متحف المحرقة في واشنطن،
and that museum is so much more comprehensive in terms of information.
وهذا المتحف هو أكثر من ذلك بكثير شامل من حيث المعلومات.
And Yad Vashem needs to deal with three million visitors a year at this point.
وياد فاشيم للتعامل مع احتياجات ثلاثة ملايين زائر سنويا في هذه المرحلة.
They said, "Let's rebuild the museum."
وقالوا، دعونا نعيد بناء المتحف.
But of course, the Sikhs might give you a job on a platter -- the Jews make it hard:
ولكن بطبيعة الحال، السيخ تعطيك وظيفة على طبق -- اليهود تجعله صعبا.
international competition, phase one, phase two, phase three.
المنافسة الدولية، المرحلة الأولى ، المرحلة الثانية ، المرحلة الثالثة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And again, I felt kind of uncomfortable with the notion
ومرة أخرى، شعرت بعدم ارتياح نوعا من فكرة
that a building the size of the Washington building --
أن بناء بحجم مبنى واشنطن،
50,000 square feet -- will sit on that fragile hill
50000 قدم مربع، تجلس على ذلك التل الهش،
and that we will go into galleries -- rooms with doors
والتي من شأنها أن نذهب إلى المعارض الفنية ، وغرف مع الأبواب
and sort of familiar rooms -- to tell the story of the Holocaust.
وترتيب غرف مألوفة لتحكي قصة المحرقة.
And I proposed that we cut through the mountain. That was my first sketch.
واقترحت أن نقطع طريق الجبل -- الذي كان رسم أول،
Just cut the whole museum through the mountain --
مجرد قطع المتحف بالكامل من خلال الجبل،
enter from one side of the mountain,
أدخل من جانب واحد من الجبل،
come out on the other side of the mountain --
يخرج من الجانب الآخر من الجبل.
and then bring light through the mountain into the chambers.
وثم جعل الضوء من خلال الجبل في الحجرات.
And here you see the model:
وهنا ترى النموذج ،
a reception building and some underground parking.
مبنى الاستقبال وبعض مواقف السيارات تحت الارض.
You cross a bridge, you enter this triangular room, 60 feet high,
تعبر الجسر ، وتدخل هذه الغرفة الثلاثية ، بارتفاع 60 قدما،
which cuts right into the hill
الذي يقطع التلة تماما
and extends right through as you go towards the north.
ويمتد الطريق تماما نحو الشمال.
And all of it, then, all the galleries are underground,
وكله، ثم، وجميع صالات العرض ، وتحت الأرض.
and you see the openings for the light.
وترى فتحات للضوء.
And at night, just one line of light cuts through the mountain,
وفي الليل، فقط سطر واحد من الضوء من يقطع خلال الجبل،
which is a skylight on top of that triangle.
وهي كوة على رأس هذا المثلث.
And all the galleries,
وجميع صالات العرض --
as you move through them and so on, are below grade.
وأنت تتحرك من خلالها، وهلم جرا -- في الدرجة أدناه.
And there are chambers carved in the rock --
وهناك غرف منحوتة في الصخر --
concrete walls, stone, the natural rock when possible -- with the light shafts.
الجدران الخرسانية، والحجر، الصخرة الطبيعية عندما يكون ذلك ممكنا -- مع أعمدة النور.
This is actually a Spanish quarry, which sort of inspired
هذا هو في الواقع المحاجر الاسبانية، والتي اوحت
the kind of spaces that these galleries could be.
هذا النوع من الأماكن التي يمكن أن تكون هذه المعارض.
And then, coming towards the north, it opens up:
ومن ثم، يأتي نحو الشمال، فإنه يفتح :
it bursts out of the mountain into, again, a view of light and of the city
انها رشقات نارية من الجبل ، ومرة أخرى، و منظر الضوء والمدينة،
and of the Jerusalem hills.
وعلى تلال القدس.
I'd like to conclude with a project I've been working on for two months.
كنت أود أن أختتم مع مشروع أعمل فيه منذ شهرين.
It's the headquarters for the Institute of Peace in Washington,
انها مقر لمعهد السلام في واشنطن،
the U.S. Institute of Peace.
معهد الولايات المتحدة للسلام.
The site chosen is across from the Lincoln Memorial;
الموقع المختار هو على الجانب الآخر من نصب لنكولن التذكاري --
you see it there directly on the Mall. It's the last building on the Mall,
كنت أنظر إليه هناك، مباشرة على مول، انها اخر بناية للمول،
on access of the Roosevelt Bridge that comes in from Virginia.
على جسر روزفلت الذي يأتي من ولاية فرجينيا.
That too was a competition, and it is something I'm just beginning to work on.
الذي كان أيضا منافسة، وهذا شيء مجرد بداية للعمل بها.
But one recognized the kind of uniqueness of the site.
ولكن يمكنك ان تعرف نوع من التفرد للموقع.
If it were to be anywhere in Washington,
إذا كانت لتكون في أي مكان في واشنطن،
it would be an office building, a conference center,
وستكون مبنى للمكاتب، ومركز المؤتمرات ،
a place for negotiating peace and so on -- all of which the building is --
مكان التفاوض من أجل السلام وهلم جرا، وكلها في المبنى.
but by virtue of the choice of putting it on the Mall and by the Lincoln Memorial,
ولكن بحكم اختيار وضعه على مول ، ونصب لنكولن التذكاري،
this becomes the structure that is the symbol of peace on the Mall.
ويصبح هذا الهيكل الذي هو رمز للسلام في مول.
And that was a lot of heat to deal with.
وأنه كان هناك الكثير من الحرارة للتعامل معها.
The first sketch recognizes that the building is many spaces --
الرسم الأول يبين بأن للمبنى مساحات كثيرة --
spaces where research goes on, conference centers,
مسافات حيث تجري البحوث، ومراكز المؤتمرات ،
a public building because it will be a museum devoted to peacemaking --
مبنى عام، لأنه سيكون المتحف المخصص لصنع السلام.
and these are the drawings that we submitted for the competition,
وهذه هي الرسومات التي قدمناها للمنافسة،
the plans showing the spaces which radiate outwards from the entry.
عرض خطط المساحات التي تشع للخارج من الدخول.
You see the structure as, in the sequence of structures on the Mall,
ترى هيكل كما هو الحال في سلسلة من الهياكل على مول :
very transparent and inviting and looking in.
شفافة جدا، وتدعو للبحث فيها.
And then as you enter it again, looking in all directions towards the city.
و عندما تدخل مرة أخرى، تبحث في كل الاتجاهات نحو المدينة.
And what I felt about that building is that it really was a building
وحول ما شعرت بأن المبنى، وأنه كان حقا مبنى
that had to do with a lightness of being -- to quote Kundera --
يتعامل بخفة مع ما يجري، على حد تعبير كونديرا --
that it had to do with whiteness,
الذي يجب ان يكون مع بياض،
it had to do with a certain dynamic quality and it had to do with optimism.
عليه أن يكون بنوعية دينامية معينة ، يشيع نوع من التفاؤل.
And this is where it is; it's sort of evolving.
وهذا هو المكان الذي هو عليه ، انه نوع من التطور.
Studies for the structure of the roof,
دراسات لهيكل السقف :
which demands maybe new materials:
التي تتطلب مواد جديدة ربما،
how to make it white, how to make it translucent, how to make it glowing,
كيفية جعله أبيض، وكيفية جعله شفاف، وكيفية جعله متوهج،
how to make it not capricious.
كيفية جعله غير متقلب.
And here studying, in three dimensions,
والدراسة هنا، في ثلاثة أبعاد،
how to give some kind, again, of order, a structure;
كيفية إعطاء نوع ما ، مرة أخرى، من أمر، هيكل،
not something you feel you could just change
لا شيء يشعرك بأنك يمكن أن تغييره
because you stop the design of that particular process.
لأنك توقف تصميم تلك العملية بالذات.
And so it goes.
و تستمر العملية.
I'd like to conclude by saying something ...
أود أن أختتم بقول شيء --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'd like to conclude by relating all of what I've said to the term "beauty."
أود أن أختتم كلمتي المتعلقة كل ما قلت لمصطلح "الجمال".
And I know it is not a fashionable term these days,
وأنا أعلم أنه ليس مصطلح مألوف في هذه الأيام ،
and certainly not fashionable in the discourse of architectural schools,
وبالتأكيد ليس من المألوف في خطاب المدارس المعمارية.
but it seems to me that all this, in one way or the other, is a search for beauty.
ولكن يبدو لي أن كل هذا، في واحدة بطريقة او اخرى، هو البحث عن الجمال.
Beauty in the most profound sense of fit.
الجمال بالمعنى الأكثر عمقا من مناسبة.
I have a quote that I like by a morphologist, 1917,
أحب ان اقتبس مورفولوجست قبل 1917،
Theodore Cook, who said, "Beauty connotes humanity.
ثيودور كوك، الذي قال : "الجمال يتضمن الإنسانية.
We call a natural object beautiful because we see
ونحن نسمي الكائنات الطبيعية جميلة لأننا نرى
that its form expresses fitness, the perfect fulfillment of function."
ان شكلها يعبر عن اللياقة البدنية ، والوفاء لكمال الوظيفة. "
Well, I would have said the perfect fulfillment of purpose.
حسنا ، هل قلت تحقيق الكمال هو الغرض.
Nevertheless, beauty as the kind of fit; something that tells us
ومع ذلك، والجمال وهذا النوع من الملائمة ، أن يقول لنا شيئا
that all the forces that have to do with our natural environment
إن جميع القوى التي لها علاقة مع بيئتنا الطبيعية
have been fulfilled -- and our human environment -- for that.
قد تم الايفاء بها -- وبيئتنا الإنسانية -- لذلك.
Twenty years ago, in a conference Richard and I were at together,
قبل 20 عاما، في مؤتمر ريتشارد وأنا في جانب،
I wrote a poem, which seems to me to still hold for me today.
كتبت قصيدة، والذي يبدو لي أنها لا تزال مناسبة حتى اليوم.
"He who seeks truth shall find beauty. He who seeks beauty shall find vanity.
واضاف "انه من يسعى الى البحث عن الحقيقة سوف يجد الجمال، والذي يسعى للجمال يجد الغرور.
He who seeks order shall find gratification.
هو الذي يسعى للبحث عن النظام، سيجد الاشباع.
He who seeks gratification shall be disappointed.
هو الذي يسعى للإشباع، سيجد خيبة أمل.
He who considers himself the servant of his fellow beings
وهو الذي يعتبر نفسه خادما للكائنات زملائه
shall find the joy of self-expression. He who seeks self-expression
سيجد الفرح في التعبير عن الذات. هو الذي يسعى للتعبير عن الذات،
shall fall into the pit of arrogance.
يسقط في حفرة الغطرسة.
Arrogance is incompatible with nature.
الغطرسة لا تتفق مع الطبيعة.
Through nature, the nature of the universe and the nature of man,
من خلال الطبيعة، طبيعة الكون وطبيعة الانسان،
we shall seek truth. If we seek truth, we shall find beauty."
وسنعمل على البحث عن الحقيقة. إذا كان لنا أن البحث عن الحقيقة، سنجد الجمال ".
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا كثيرا جدا.